<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/*
 * Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 * 
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
 -->
	
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Maven Environment for Turbine Applications (M.E.T.A.)</title>
    <author email="hps@intermeta.de">Henning P. Schmiedehausen</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Maven Environment for Turbine Applications (M.E.T.A.)">
<p>
The Maven Environment for Turbine Application (M.E.T.A.) helps you to write
applications based on the <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/">Turbine Webapplication
framework</a>.
</p>
</section>

<section name="How it works">
<p>
M.E.T.A. builds an application skeleton from a set of prebuilt
configuration files and some user supplied parameters. Most of the
parameters have reasonable defaults, only the application name must be
supplied at setup time.
<br/>
Parameters are supplied either on the command line (if you want to
rapid prototype an application, you can do so by running <a
href="getting_started.html#singlecommand">a single command</a>)
or with a special properties file, which is read by M.E.T.A. when you
setup your appliation. Please see the <a
href="getting_started.html">Getting Started</a> page for a reference
on how to bootstrap your application.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Maven Integration">
<p>
M.E.T.A. is installed as a <a
href="http://maven.apache.org/">maven</a> plugin and has goals and
properties.
</p>

<subsection name="Goals">
<p>
All M.E.T.A. goals are prefixed by "turbine" in the maven
environment. While &quot;meta&quot; is distinctive in the Turbine
context, using meta:&lt;xxx&gt; as goal names proved confusing in the
Maven context (is meta:&lt;xxx&gt; a maven meta-goal or is it part of
the M.E.T.A.  environment?). So the M.E.T.A. environment uses the
"turbine:" prefix.<br/>
The available goals are listed on the <a href="goals.html">Goals</a> page.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Properties">
<p>
To adjust the various parameters of the plugin to your application,
you must set properties in your <code>project.properties</code> or
<code>build.properties</code> file. Most of the properties have a
reasonable default. You can find the complete list of properties on
the <a href="properties.html">Properties</a> page. If you use the <a
href="goals.html#turbine_setup">turbine:setup</a> goal from M.E.T.A.,
these properties are preset either from the command line parameters or
from the parameters set in the setup properties file.
<br/>
As M.E.T.A. tries to integrate with the maven web application environment
as seamlessly as possible, it requires a few properties from other
plugins to be set.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
