<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- 
/*
 * Copyright 2001-2004 The Apache Software Foundation.
 * 
 * Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
 * you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
 * You may obtain a copy of the License at
 * 
 *      http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0
 * 
 * Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
 * distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
 * WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
 * See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
 * limitations under the License.
 */
 -->
	
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Maven Environment for Turbine Applications (META)</title>
    <author email="hps@intermeta.de">Henning P. Schmiedehausen</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
<section name="Maven Environment for Turbine Applications (META)">
<p>
The Maven Environment for Turbine Application (META) is an easy way to
get started with applications based on the Turbine Webapplication
framework and also a collection of &quot;best practices&quot; and
configuration information to get you started with writing code using
the Turbine framework.
</p>
</section>

<section name="How it works">
<p>
META builds an application skeleton from a set of prebuilt
configuration files and some user supplied parameters. Most of the
parameters have reasonable defaults, only the application name must be
supplied by the developer.
<br/>
Parameters are supplied either on the command line (if you want to
rapid prototype an application, you can do so by running a single
maven command) or with a special properties file that will be read by
the META task. Please see the <a href="getting_started.html">Getting Started</a>
page for a reference on how to bootstrap your application.
</p>
</section>
<section name="Maven Integration">
<p>
META is installed as a maven plugin and has goals and properties.
</p>

<subsection name="Goals">
<p>
All META goals are prefixed by "turbine" in the maven
environment. While META is distinctive in the Turbine context, using
meta:&lt;xxx&gt; proved confusing in the Maven context (is meta:&lt;xxx&gt; a
maven meta-task or is it part of the META environment?). So the META
environment uses the "turbine:" prefix.<br/>

The available goals are listed on the <a href="goals.html">Goals</a> page.
</p>
</subsection>
<subsection name="Properties">
<p>
To adjust the various plugin tasks to your application, you must set a few
properties in your project.properties or build.properties file. Most of the
properties have a reasonable default. You can find the complete list of properties
on the <a href="properties.html">Properties</a> page.
<br/>
As META tries to integrate with the maven web application environment
as seamlessly as possible, it requires a few properties from other
plugins to be set.
</p>
</subsection>
</section>
</body>
</document>
