<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
    <properties>
        <title>"Simple" Intake How-to for Turbine 2.1</title>
        <author email="dantest@yorku.ca">Daniel Kha</author>
        <author email="seade@backstagetech.com.au">Scott Eade</author>
    </properties>

    <body>
        <section name="Introduction">
            <p>
                First of all I'd like to note that this document is based on my
                experience in using Intake for Turbine 2.1.  I've tried to make
                it as correct as possible but I don't guarantee anything.  This
                has been written as a guide for a new Intake user and assumes
                some familiarity with Turbine 2.1.
            </p>
            <p>
                To use intake, the following steps are required:

                <ol>
                    <li>Create your turbine template with a form.</li>
                    <li>Create the intake.xml file.</li>
                    <li>Create a business object to represent the intake group
                        we are working with (this is optional).</li>
                    <li>Create the Turbine Action to handle the form
                        submission.</li>
                </ol>
            </p>
            <p>
                Some additional information concerning removing Intake group
                information from the request is included at the bottom of this
                document.
            </p>
        </section>

        <section name="Step 1: Create your turbine template with a form">
            <p>
                The first thing to do is the create the form in your template
                (e.g. a velocity template file, a .vm file).  Just create the
                skeleton structure and don't worry about the field names and
                values yet.  Note that field names will have to match the names
                specified in the intake.xml file.  Actually you can do the
                opposite (name the fields here first and match them in the
                intake.xml file) if you wish, but this guide will do it the
                former way.
            </p>
            <p>
                Now add the following lines above the code for your form and
                modify it to match the group and field names in your intake.xml
                file (perhaps you can come back to do this step after you've
                done your intake.xml file).  Here is an example in a Velocity
                template for a "login form":
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
#set($loginGroup = $intake.LoginGroup.Default)
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                What this does is to set a Velocity variable called $loginGroup
                to a default group object specified by intake.xml.  The $intake
                variable is the Turbine Pull Tool instance (IntakeTool).  The
                "LoginGroup" is the name of the group as specified in the
                intake.xml file (names must match, and this is not the group's
                key attribute.).  The "Default" part obtains a generic default
                intake group object. Or in other words, this resolves to
                IntakeTool.get(String groupName) with the groupName being
                "LoginGroup".  Also, you can re-write the statement as
                $intake.get("LoginGroup").getDefault() in your template.
            </p>
            <p>
                Or if you would like to map the intake group to a business
                object (for whatever purpose) then you can do this (read on
                for more info on what is required to do this in intake.xml and
                the corresponding Turbine Action class):
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
#set($loginGroup = $intake.LoginGroup.mapTo($mytool.getInstanceLoginForm()))
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                What this does is to set a Velocity variable called $loginGroup
                to an instance of the LoginForm business object (and if the
                returned object has values in its fields and appropriate
                "getter" methods then this would prepopulate the intake group
                with the values.  A good usage example of this is when you
                would like to prepopulate the form with values from the
                database and want to use intake to validate the form).  It
                makes use of a custom tool placed into the Velocity context as
                "$mytool" (you can make your own tool to instantiate an instance
                of your business object similar to this example).
            </p>
            <p>
                So, depending on the method you use above, the corresponding
                Turbine Action code will need to "cooperate" accordingly.
                We'll discuss this later in step 4.
            </p>
            <p>
                Near the end of the form (before you close the "form" tag)
                include the following line:
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
$intake.declareGroups()
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                What this does is to fill in hidden form fields into the form
                for use by intake.
            </p>
            <p>
                In order to use Turbine's Action event system, the submit buttons
                must adhere to the naming specification defined by
                <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-2/howto/action-event-howto.html">
                Turbine's Action event system</a>.
            </p>

            <subsection name="*** IMPORTANT NOTE ***">
                <p>
                    If you use
                    $link.setAction('SomeAction').setPage('NextTemplate.vm')
                    in your form's action attribute like this:
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
<form name="myForm" method="POST"
      action="$link.setAction('LoginAction').setPage('NextTemplate.vm')">
    ...
</form>
                ]]></source>
                <p/>
                <p>
                    then the form validation won't appear to work (i.e. the user
                    will see the NextTemplate.vm file instead of the form they
                    were trying to fill out which failed validation).  To work
                    around this problem, you can omit the setPage('...') part
                    in your form's action attribute and then have your action
                    route the user to the next template on validation success
                    OR somehow detect the current form the user is at and if
                    the validation fails, override the next template to the
                    current template (which is really just overriding the
                    setPage() part in the template file specified by the web
                    designer).
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="Step 2: Create the intake.xml file">
            <p>
                The intake.xml file specifies the validation rules required to
                be satisfied in order for the form to be accepted.  The file has
                a "root" XML element of "input-data" and in that would be
                "group" elements.
            </p>
            <p>
                Here is an example of the element (with no other sub-elements):
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE input-data SYSTEM
           "http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/dtd/intake_2_2_1.dtd">
<input-data basePackage="ca.yorku.devteam.inca.clients.skeleton.">
    ...group elements goes here...
</input-data>
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                Notice the basePackage attribute (optional) points to the
                skeleton package with an extra period at the end.  This
                attribute specifies the package that contains the java objects
                the "group" and "field" elements can optionally map to.
                The trailing period is REQUIRED.
            </p>

            <subsection name="&lt;group&gt; elements">
                <p>
                    Each group element represents a collection of field information you'd like to
                    validate in your form.  For example, on a login page you would have a form for
                    the user to input their username and password, and as well as a login button.
                    This entire form would be grouped as a group in the intake.xml file.
                </p>
                <p>
                    Here is an example of a group with no other elements (not useful yet):
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
<group name="LoginGroup" key="loginGroupKey" mapToObject="LoginForm">
    ...field elements goes here...
</group>
                ]]></source>
                <p/>
                <p>
                    A group element can have the following attributes:

                    <ul>
                        <li>"name" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    the name of the group, is required, and must
                                    be unique across the entire intake.xml file.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <ul>
                        <li>"key" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    the key of the group, is required, and must
                                    be unique across the entire intake.xml file.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <ul>
                        <li>"mapToObject" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    optional, used if you want to map the form
                                    to a business object. Note that the field
                                    names specified later by the "field" element
                                    in the group should match the field names of
                                    the business object with appropriate get/set
                                    methods.  See the "field" tag examples to
                                    find how to override this default behaviour.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    For a complete list of valid attributes of the group
                    element, please see the
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-2/services/intake-service.html">
                    intake-service document</a> on the Turbine web site.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="&lt;field&gt; elements">
                <p>
                    Each group element can contain any number of "field"
                    elements.  Each field element will correspond to a field in
                    the form.  The name and key of each field will be used in
                    the form code in the template so make sure the names and
                    keys match in both files (intake.xml and the template file).
                </p>
                <p>
                    Here is an example of a field with no other elements (not
                    too useful yet):
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
<field name="Username" key="loginUsernameKey" type="String"
        mapToProperty="Username">
    ...rule elements goes here...
</field>
                ]]></source>
                <p/>
                <p>
                    A field element can have the following attributes:

                    <ul>
                        <li>"name" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    the name of the field, is required, and must
                                    be unique across the entire group element.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <ul>
                        <li>"key" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    the key of the field, is required, and must
                                    be unique across the entire group element.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <ul>
                        <li>"type" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    required, the type of the field so that
                                    intake will know what to expect.  Valid
                                    types I know of are: String, Integer (I
                                    believe these map to the corresponding Java
                                    types).  Please see the intake.dtd for the
                                    allowed values.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>

                    <ul>
                        <li>"mapToProperty" attribute
                            <ul>
                                <li>
                                    optional, used if you want to map the form
                                    to a business object.  Note that the field
                                    names specified in this "field" element
                                    should match the field name of the business
                                    object with appropriate get/set methods.
                                </li>
                            </ul>
                        </li>
                    </ul>
                </p>
                <p>
                    For a complete list of valid attributes of the field
                    element, please see the
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-2/services/intake-service.html">
                    intake-service document</a> on the Turbine web site.
                </p>
            </subsection>

            <subsection name="&lt;rule&gt; elements">
                <p>
                    In each field element, you can have rules defined.  The
                    supported rule elements for Intake in Turbine 2.1 are:
                </p>
                <source><![CDATA[
<rule name="required" value="true">Error message for required failed</rule>
<rule name="minLength" value="4">Error message for required min length failed</rule>
<rule name="maxLength" value="9">Error message for required max length failed</rule>
<rule name="mask" value="^[0-9]+$">Error message for regular expression failed</rule>
                ]]></source>
                <p/>
                <p>
                    For more info on the supported rules, please see the
                    <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/turbine/turbine-2/services/intake-service.html">
                    intake-service document</a> on the Turbine web site:
                </p>
            </subsection>
        </section>

        <section name="Step 3: Create a business object to represent the intake group we are working with (this is optional).">
            <p>
                The business object is basically a Java class that has get and
                set methods for each of the object's fields, and these get and
                set method names should match the field names specified in the
                intake.xml file (whether we stay with the default behaviour of
                matching the field names in intake.xml and the business object
                or we use the mapToProperty attribute in the "field" element).
                Note it is required to use the mapToObject property in the group
                element to use this feature.
            </p>
            <p>
                The business object also has to implement the
                org.apache.turbine.om.Retrievable interface.  The Retrievable
                was designed to work with a database so the methods
                get/setQueryKey doesn't make much sense if your business object
                isn't based on a database model.  For my use, I just force the
                key to be "_0" which is the default key used by Intake (as of
                Turbine 2.1).  You could, of course, implement it as a normal
                data field to allow the template to set the query key and then
                in the Action to get the query key.  But then you'll have to
                keep track of the key you use in both the template file and
                Action class (the benefit would be that you'll be able to use
                more than 1 business object in the same template if you get/set
                the different query keys).
            </p>
            <p>
                Here is an example of how to use the setQueryKey() and
                getQueryKey() methods of the business object that implements
                the Retrievable interface:
            </p>
            <p>
                In the template file, e.g. myform.vm:
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
#set($loginForm = $mytool.getLoginFormInstance())
$loginForm.setQueryKey("abc")
#set($loginGroup = $intake.LoginGroup.mapTo($loginForm))
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                In the Action class:
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
// This key has to match the one in the template
String key = "abc";
Group group = intake.get("LoginGroup", key);
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
        </section>

        <section name="Step 4: Create the Turbine Action to handle the form submission.">
            <p>
                Depending on the method you use, the code in the action will
                need to obtain the corresponding group object from intake.  The
                following examples will demonstrate the ideas.
            </p>
            <p>
                Here is an example the code in a Turbine Action, using intake
                without mapping to a business object (vanilla method):
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
/**
 * Performs user login
 */
public void doLogin(RunData data, Context context)
        throws Exception {
    // Get intake group
    IntakeTool intake =
            (IntakeTool)context.get("intake");

    // Notice how this gets the group named "LoginGroup" as defined in
    // the intake.xml file, and gets it using the default key
    // IntakeTool.DEFAULT_KEY (which is "_0").
    Group group = intake.get("LoginGroup", IntakeTool.DEFAULT_KEY);

    // Check if group fields are valid and if they are not, then return.
    // Intake will handle the validation error and display the
    // corresponding error messages to the user but if you use the setPage()
    // mechanism to get the "next template" then you must now set the
    // template to be the same one as the user was filling out.  Otherwise
    // the user will just see the next template.  See the "important note"
    // in step 1.
    if (!group.isAllValid()) {
        Log.debug("Group elements INVALID");
        setTemplate(data, "Login.vm");
        return;
    } else {
        // If all is validated then you can set the next template and/or
        // continue processing...it's up to you.  You can also use
        // setPage() in the template file to set the next template to show
        // on successful validation.
        setTemplate(data, "LoginSuccess.vm");
    }

    // This gets the value of the "Username" field from the group object
    String username = (String)group.get("Username").getValue();
    String password = (String)group.get("Password").getValue();

    // Now you will be able to use the username and password variable in
    // the rest of the Turbine Action.
    ...
}
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                Here is example code in a Turbine Action, using the intake
                group's default mapToObject setting (this is the same whether
                or not you use the field's mapToProperty attribute):
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
/**
 * Performs user login
 */
public void doLogin(RunData data, Context context)
        throws Exception {
    // Get intake group
    IntakeTool intake =
            (IntakeTool)context.get("intake");
    Group group = intake.get("LoginGroup", IntakeTool.DEFAULT_KEY);

    // Check if group fields are valid and if they are not, then return.
    // Intake will handle the validation error and display the
    // corresponding error messages to the user but if you use the setPage()
    // mechanism to get the "next template" then you must now set the
    // template to be the same one as the user was filling out.  Otherwise
    // the user will just see the next template.  See the "important note"
    // in step 1.
    if (!group.isAllValid()) {
        Log.debug("Group elements INVALID");
        setTemplate(data, "Login.vm");
        return;
    } else {
        // If all is validated then you can set the next template and/or
        // continue processing...it's up to you.  You can also use
        // setPage() in the template file to set the next template to show
        // on successful validation.
        setTemplate(data, "LoginSuccess.vm");
    }

    // Instaniate a business object that represents the form
    LoginForm loginForm = new LoginForm();

    // Set the properties of the form given the field data in the group
    // (i.e. populate the business object)
    group.setProperties(loginForm);

    // Now the business object is populated accordingly.  You can use it
    // for whatever purpose in the rest of the Turbine Action.
    ...
}
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
        </section>
        <section name="Removing Intake information from the request">
            <p>
                Intake data is retained in the request in order to allow for the
                possibility that it will be re-presented to the user on the next
                page. Normally this is desirable behaviour - there may have been
                an error in the data so you want to redisplay it. There is a
                possibility however that you might want to reuse the same group
                on either the same or a different page after fully processing
                the data; in this case it may be undesirable to redisplay the
                previously entered data. The prime example of this is where a
                page includes a repeating group of records and provides an
                opportunity to add a further record using the default group,
                returning to the same page after each record is added.  In this
                situation you will find that the default group needs to be
                removed from the request, otherwise the data entered on the
                previous page will be redisplayed.
            </p>
            <p>
                Intake allows for this by providing a way of removing the data
                that is no longer appropriate to display.  Simply:
            </p>
            <source><![CDATA[
intake.remove(group);
            ]]></source>
            <p/>
            <p>
                ... where "intake" is a reference to your IntakeTool and "group"
                is a reference to the group you wish to remove from the
                request.  You would do this after the new record had been
                validated and added to the database.
            </p>
            <p>
                It will be rare that you actually need to do this - it is
                required only in situations where the same group is used on
                subsequent pages after the data has been fully processed (it
                should be pretty obvious when this is the case).
            </p>
        </section>
    </body>
</document>
