<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
 <properties>
  <title>Turbine Todo</title>
  <author email="celkins@scardini.com">Christopher Elkins</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Todo">

<p>

  This document describes functionality that is either missing or not finished
  within Turbine as well as the owners of implementing or coordinating the
  implementation of these features.

</p>

<p>

  Wish List functionality is stuff that we would like to see implemented, but is
  not critical for release. This is the area where you can take ownership of a
  part of the project and contribute back.

</p>

<p>

  Critical Before Release is stuff that we feel is holding up the release of
  Turbine.

</p>

<p>

  If you are a new developer to Turbine or even an existing developer, these are
  areas where you can take ownership and help complete. Please do not ask us how
  you can help, but rather specific questions about how you think that these items
  should be implemented. It is up to you to take initiative and provide solutions
  to the missing functionality described below. ;-)

</p>

<p>

  It is always possible to take ownership of any portion of the project. The way
  to do this is to communicate with the owner of the portion and then come to some
  sort of agreement about what portions you will be splitting up or taking over.
  If you cannot get a response from the people in charge of the projects, assume
  they are dead and fill yourself in.

</p>

<p>

  Documentation is <b>*always*</b> appreciated in any form. There are two ways to
  provide helpful documentation. The first way is to write up XML documentation and
  send it to one of the primary authors directly (we are also
  willing to give you CVS write access if you wish). The second way is to post
  Questions/Answers to the <a href="http://java.apache.org/jyve-faq/Turbine">
  FAQ</a> under the Turbine sections there. Please review the sections in the
  <a href="turbine-documentation-project.html">Turbine Documentation Project</a>
  for ways to get started and areas of documentation needing attention. You need
  to take the initiative and just start writing down your thoughts and concerns
  and questions and answers and then giving those back to us.

</p>

<p>

  If you need more detailed help, please send mail to the
  <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/mail.html">mailing list</a> and ask
  your specific questions there.

</p>

</section>

<section name="Wish List">

<ul>
  <li>

    Documentation improvements - The website is checked into CVS and can
    be edited by anyone. If you are new to Turbine and are just learning
    things, documenting what you learn and adding it to our website
    would be appreciated.

    <p>

       More detail on how you can contribute
       documentation is contained in the
       <a href="turbine-documentation-project.html">Turbine Documentation Project</a> page.

    </p>

  </li>

  <li>

    Implement more robust multipart message handling
    (org/apache/turbine/util/mail)

    <p>
      Owner: None
    </p>

  </li>

  <li>

    Well thought out (and executed) Cocoon 2 Implementation
    <p>

      Owner: None (potential <a href="mailto:jon@latchkey.com">Jon
      S.Stevens</a> and Kevin Burton)</p>
      <p>Co-Owner: (Giacomo Pati has expressed interest)

    </p>

  </li>

  <li>

    We can always use additional utility code that goes into the <code>util</code> directory.
    Send us whatever you can along the lines of what <code>BrowserDetector</code> and
    <code>DateSelector</code> provide. This is your chance to contribute your useful classes
    to a wider audience and get feedback and support!

    <p>
      Owner: None
    </p>
  </li>
  <li>
      Unit tests are greatly needed for nearly all areas of the project.
  </li>

</ul>
<p>
    The most current version of this list can be found on the
    <a href="http://nagoya.apache.org/wiki/apachewiki.cgi?JakartaTurbine2/WishList">Apache Wiki</a>

</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
