<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>

 <properties>
  <title>The Turbine Documentation Project</title>
  <author email="criley@ekmail.com">Cameron Riley</author>
  <author email="jon@latchkey.com">Jon S. Stevens</author>
 </properties>

<body>

<section name="Turbine Documentation Project">

<p>
The Turbine Documentation Project is the process of documenting Turbine, inside
and out, for the user community. Opensource projects live and die by their
community participation, as a software project is more than just source code,
other components such as documentation have an important role in the process.
As Software Engineers tend towards the habit of communicating in code,
documentation is often skimped on, which can alienate the new or less
experienced user. This component of the Turbine project will formalise the
common and shared knowledge of the Turbine community into documentation for
Software Engineers, Students, Hobbyists and interested passers-by alike. This
however requires participation from all members of the Turbine User community.
</p>

</section>

<section name="What Can I do to Contribute?">

<p>
Turbine can always improve it's documentation, there are many area's that always
need attention;
</p>

<ul>
<li>Correct Errors.</li>
<li>Correct spelling mistakes.</li>
<li>Replace out of date information.</li>
<li>Improve existing documentation.</li>
<li>Add new documentation.</li>
</ul>

<p>
There are more specific and immediate documentation needs in the TODO section
below. If you are looking for an aspect of Turbine to start learn and document
immediately, the ToDo is a good start. Documenting has the added advantage, that
it is an excellent way to learn Turbine in detail and become an advanced Turbine
user!
</p>

</section>

<section name="Documentation ToDo List">

<ul>
<li>Fix spelling and grammatical errors.</li>
</ul>

<ul>
<li>Turbine and Security - There needs to be more documentation on Security
management.</li>
<li>Turbine and LDAP - Security with LDAP</li>
<li>Turbine and Javascript - Loading js files through ContentURI</li> 
<li>Turbine and JSP - Needs jsp examples.</li>
<li>Turbine and Python - Needs Python examples.</li>
<li>Turbine and Frames - Needs to be in it's own document.</li>
</ul>

<ul>
<li>Screens and Actions - How the Default Screen and Action work.</li> 
<li>Pull Howto</li>
<li>Torque Howto - including OM description</li> 
<li>Intake Howto</li>
<li>Advanced Criteria - needs more description of comparitors and Criterion.
</li> 
<li>Services - All the services need documentation.</li>
</ul>

<p>
TDK Howto - Howto or tutorial describing initial app to creating your own
schema, om/peer classes, business objects through to Velocity Templates.
</p>

<p>
Plus more .....
</p>

</section>

<section name="Website Documentation">

<p>
The website documentation is the main component outside of the source code and
javadocs. If there are ommisions on the website that you think need to be
documented or written in, please go ahead and do it.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Turbine and TDK Feature Documentation">

<p>
Turbine is a complex system with numerous features  The features that make up
Turbine all need documenting.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Turbine and TDK Internal Workings Documentation">

<p>
How the components at the source level work, such as the Assemblers, Services,
Actions and Screens, Connection Pooling etc.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Turbine and TDK Tutorials">

<p>
How to use Turbine with other technologies such as JSP, JBoss etc etc How to use
Torque, how to get a tdk project up and running. How to use the objects in
Turbine for your projects such As Peers and Criteria.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Filtering Mailing Lists">

<p>
Monitor mailing lists for common discussions and modify into a format that is
sutiable for the Turbine Website and xdocs directory, plus adding a few choice
comments. From there it can be improved.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Javadocing Source Code">

<p>
Javadocing the source code where it is missing, incomplete or can be described
better. As this is an opensource project the source code is open to all who wish
to view it, having well documented, clean, understandable code is important.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Getting Started">

<p>
To get started, read all the current documentation and find an area that you
know a bit about. If that area isnt covered, you can improve Turbine by
documenting it. Write up the document, no matter how skeletal and email it to
the Turbine-Users-List, making sure your are subscribed first. All documentation
of any kind is greatly appreciated.
</p>

<p>
The documentation is maintained as XML in the /jakarta-turbine/xdocs directory,
and are transformed to HTML for the website documentation.
</p>

</section>

<section name="Building the Docs">

<p>
To build the HTML docs you need to <a
href="http://jakarta.apache.org/site/jakarta-site2.html">check out the
jakarta-site2 project from CVS</a>.
</p>

<p>
To check that the xml document you have built is validated, run it through the
build process. To do this cd to the build directory and execute the
<strong>docs</strong> target:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
ant docs
]]></source>

<p>
This will transform all the XML files in the /jakarta-turbine/xdocs directory to
HTML in the docs directory. Any validation erros will be thrown while processing
giving a line number for the XML file where the XML is incorrect. Usually it is
something minor like an unclosed tag or a spelling error in a tag.
</p>

<p>
If you are a committer, don't forget to check in the html-files and update the
web-site. Log into apache.org and type:
</p>

<source><![CDATA[
umask 002
cd /www/jakarta.apache.org/turbine
cvs update
]]></source>

<p>
That will update the live website. The umask line you can put into your
.cshrc/.tcshrc/.bashrc so that you only have to do it once.
</p>

</section>

</body>
</document>
